TSMC has made a major breakthrough in next-gen memory
Does it mean Samsung is losing the throne to TSMC?
Even in the memory sector?
In early 2024
ITRI and TSMC announced
they will co-release the world’s fastest MRAM
SOT-MRAM
It could take the lead in the market of
Next-Gen AI memory
The new-type memory not only accesses data extremely fast
with low power consumption
It will surely be more and more crucial in the future
with larger and larger servers
What’s great with this memory is
It’s not bothered by blackouts
It doesn’t lose its data
All great things in one
How did they make it?
Besides MRAM
What other new-type memories
will be the ace of manufacturers
in the memory market?
We mentioned in the last episode
to swiftly load and save data
it’s better to use capacitors
rather than heavy magnets
A transistor plus a capacitor
is the simplest memory unit
With or without electricity in the capacitor
means 1 or 0 as a digital bit
When you need to load data
or rewrite it
Just turn on the switch of transistors
to load or write with capacitors
But in reality, it’s not that easy
Even if the transistor is off
It still leaks electricity slowly
So the design needs to
recharge the capacitor constantly
to refresh memory
We can’t just call it leaking memory
so it’s called “dynamic” random access memory
written as Dynamic RAM
or the acronym DRAM
And if there’s
a long blackout
the electricity in the capacitors will drain out
All the temporarily saved data
will disappear
So, this memory
is also called volatile memory
If the data needs to be preserved for a long time
You can’t put it here
It has to be saved in hard disc drive or USB flash drive
In “non-volatile” flash memory
volatile and non-volatile memories
each has its own demerits
For example, DRAM of volatile memories
needs to be constantly recharged
In reality, the frequency is about once every 64 milliseconds
15.6 times per second
When a computer has to add memory
especially now with AI models
AI PCs
AI phones
that evolve endlessly
These computers
will grow to be power-devouring monsters
And non-volatile memories
have their problems too
Though flash memory among them
doesn’t lose data during a blackout
Yet in the process of frequent writing and erasing data
High voltage will gradually damage the oxide layers in structure
So the write-in times of a flash memory
is limited
Short life is the demerit
Besides, the greatest defect is
loading and writing speed much slower than DRAM
namely
in the next-gen memory market
the goal is really clear
Can we develop a memory
with combined merits
which is fast
long-life
energy-saving
and not bothered by blackouts
To develop a new-type memory
Scientists began to research with different materials and structures
One of them is magnetoresistive memory
MRAM
It means literally
to store data with magnetic force
Wait a minute
Didn’t we say in the last episode that
magnetism is an option
eliminated in the 1970s?
Well, it is
But previous magnets were big and heavy
The magnets used this time
are much smaller than those in the 1970s
We must look further into the origin
How on earth did the magnets
produce their magnetism?
The principle behind it is quite complicated
Let’s just take the
most simplified version
Try to imagine
a magnet consists of many
tiny weeny magnets
The little magnets are electrons in the material
Why are electrons magnetic?
In quantum dynamics
you can’t visually observe every electron rotating
but there’s a quantum feature called spin
This spin generates magnetism
and the magnetic force points to a specific direction
like a small compass
OK, to understand how MRAM works
this is all we need to know
magnetism is related to electron spin
And the direction of that spin
is related to the magnetized direction
Here comes the point
When an electron tries to
pass through some magnetized material
if its spin is consistent
with the material’s magnetized direction
It can easily pass through
like merging into its own kind
Contrarily
if an electron tries to pass through a bunch of
peers with opposite spin direction
It will be seriously obstructed
namely confronting larger resistance
It’s called the giant magnetoresistance effect
Though there are records of humans
using magnets before Christ
the giant magnetoresistance
wasn’t discovered until 1988
and it won the Nobel Prize in physics in 2007
How can we use the giant magnetoresistance
to design memories?
Just like a capacitor stores 1 and 0
by the status of with or without electricity
giant magnetoresistance
can represent 1 and 0
by the status of low and high resistance
In MRAM
There are two magnetic materials
clamping a non-magnetic material
The purpose is
to control the magnetized direction of
each magnetized material
the spin direction of an electron is not fixed in a circuit
There are up and down
Yet when two materials
both got magnetized direction upwards
a spin upward electron
can easily pass through the first
and the second
the whole resistance is smaller
And if the magnetized directions of two materials
are opposite
Whether it’s upward
or downward
It’s hard for an electron to pass through both materials
This is when the whole resistance value gets larger
In real memory frameworks
It’s usually made as a double ferromagnetic layer
The magnetized direction of one layer is fixed
to the right, for example
then write the bit in the second layer
make the magnetized direction to the right if you want to record 1
The magnetized direction to the left
If it’s a 0
The direction will be kept
When you load data later
If the current goes from up to down
measure the value of resistance
You know the magnetized directions of the two layers
are consistent or opposite
get the 1 or 0 result by it
That’s how magnetoresistive memory works
The merit of magnetoresistive memory is
magnetism can be stored for a long time
hence a non-volatile memory
Compared to the magnetic core memory used in the 1960s
that we mentioned in the last episode
The unit is small
and convenient to access
almost like a DRAM
Surely MRAM has its bottleneck in development
that’s how to control precisely
the magnetized direction of a thin ferromagnetic layer
without affecting other bits
The earliest way is to put a wire
around the ferromagnetic layer
use the electromagnetic field generated by the current in the wire
to change the polarized direction
But to prevent the wire-generated magnetic field
from affecting the bits around
every memory unit has to keep a certain distance
from each other
It’s a huge limitation for downsizing
so it’s hard for MRAM to be competitive
until around the year 2000 AD
Scientists made a major discovery
making MRAM to come back
If we let a current pass through
some upward-polarized magnet layer first
to screen the electrons
most of the rest are upward rotating electrons
then let the current pass through
a second unpolarized ferromagnetic layer
It would apply a moment of force
to the electrons in the second layer of material
forcing them to turn to the same rotating direction
It’s like a group of dancers with specific steps
entering the pool
to change the step direction of the entire pool
Rotating polarized electrons
also change the magnetized direction of the magnetic material
without an external magnetic field
The phenomenon is called
“Spin-transfer torque”
In short, STT
Compared to the way we just mentioned , using the external wire-generated
magnetic field to change the magnetized direction
STT doesn’t need an external magnetic field
simply change the ferromagnetic layer’s polarized direction
by a current
to write the bit
without affecting nearby bits
So it solved the problem of
bits cannot get too close
The product using STT technology
is called STT-MRAM
It fulfills the demand for modern computing size
hence in 2006
became the first batch of commercially mass-produced MRAM
To understand the latest progress in this realm
we must ask the experts, of course
Today we’re honored to have a special guest
professor Hu Bi-he of the Department of Electrical Engineering, NTU
to share with us the latest progress in next-gen memory
Professor Hu, we’d like to know
we saw the ITRI & TSMC
released in 2024
a new product called SOT-MRAM
What’s the difference with
what we mentioned earlier as STT-MRAM
that was popular several years ago?
The so-called SOT means
Spin Orbit Torque
Its write-in operation mode is different from STT
using the spin Hall effect
The write-in mode of SOT-MRAM
isn’t using the spinning polarized current
through the magnetic material layers
but to let the current
flow by them
Separating the current routes of
write-in and loading
make the memory significantly superior
in terms of operation speed
also reduce the power consumption
Besides the SOT-MRAM released by TSMC
we’ve actually heard of many different types of memories
Can you elaborate on them for us
what’s different about them?
Besides SOT-MRAM
There are actually at least three other types
of mainstream emerging memory technologies
Firstly, I’ll introduce a type called resistive random access memory
RRAM in short
The RRAM
has two metal layers
clamping a layer of transition metal oxide
to form a sandwich structure
changes the resistance value of the transition metal oxide
by applying different voltages
to the states of 0 and 1
This is the first type of resistive memory
The second type is called
phase-change memory
Its structure also looks like a sandwich
but the middle layer material
consists of vulcanized chalcogenide
a glass-like material
By heating it up
you can change the chalcogenide layer
Its crystal phase
can make it a multi-crystal state
or a non-crystal status
getting various resistance values
by changing the crystal phase
to make a state of 0 or 1
The third type of memory
is ferroelectric RAM
Ferroelectric RAM is actually quite an old memory
Conventionally, we use Perovskite
as the ferromagnetic layer material
But in 2011
Scientists found a kind of
widely used
high dielectric coefficient semiconductor material
called hafnium oxide
At the technology node of 4 to 5 nanometers
it can be introduced to minimize
transistors’ effective thickness of the Gate Oxide
Scientists found in 2011
it’s has a ferroelectric feature besides its high dielectric coefficient
This drew interest because
a widely used material
means it does not pollute
or disrupt the entire production line
hence highly acceptable
There have been many research projects in recent years
progressing rapidly
The operation of Ferroelectric RAM
largely relies on a ferroelectric layer
and the reversible electric dipole in it
By reversing the positive and negative charge direction of electric dipole
it allows the current of transistors beneath
flow through more easily
or with more resistance
making a high or low current state
to form 0 and 1 states
Do you believe these next-gen memories
will change the entire memory market?
Can it change the entire memory market
I think the idea might not exactly
a concept widely accepted
What we have to consider is whether these emerging memories
be used to compensate for
the gap in the existing memory hierarchy framework
The memory hierarchy framework we have now
we haven’t mention previously
we haven’t mentioned previously
The fastest would be S-RAM
which is a cache memory
then comes the main memory, DRAM
Their operation speeds are both at the nanosecond level
Very fast
But SRAM requires the most basic memory unit
of at least six transistors
so it’s bulky
bulky means high cost
It can’t be of a very large capacity
like other memories
That’s right
Besides SRAM & DRAM with high operating speed
USB drives or solid state drives
people use frequently
use a technology
we call flash memory
That’s right
The merit of flash memory is its low cost
also its high capacity
People’s hard disc drives typically have at least
1TB to over 2TB
but their operation speed is much slower
at the microsecond level
So you can imagine
nanosecond & microsecond levels
in the system
with a significant speed gap in between
The greatest potential of emerging memories is
their ability to make up for this speed gap
There’s a wonderful merit in the meantime
It’s a non-volatile memory
just like flash memory
That’s right
A so-called non-volatile memory means
when you turn off the power
the data remains
the homework and photos students saved
are in this type of non-volatile memory
Volatile memory
is what we mentioned of higher speed
SRAM and DRAM
Only when we boot the computer
turn on the power
can it load data saved somewhere else
as temporary stored memory
But they can’t store your homework
or photos
That’s a gap
Emerging memories have got higher speed
operating near the nanosecond level
while remaining non-volatile
Hopefully it can make up for
the existing memory hierarchy gap
To make the system achive
better performance at a lower cost
So I wouldn’t say that emerging memories
will change the entire memory market
What we should consider is whether these emerging memories
make up for what can’t be done now
make the whole system operate with
better performance
Emerging memories are still very promising
even the MRAM we discussed the most in this episode
People have long expected it to be
an universal memory
MRAM itself also operates at the nanosecond level
It can probably replace
the slowest rank of cache memory
which is jokingly called the last cache memory
with being non-volatile
You can minimize power consumption
because you don’t need to reload the data
to recovery
It’s a non-volatile feature
With more read/write cycles
With more load/write times
there’s a potential to replace existing cache memory
that we use as a storage device
These emerging memories
have great potential depending on
different applications
If we try to make a demand list
for memory
or predict which type will prevail
in reality
is like this:
We can’t simply rely on just one type of memory
We need to integrate the merits of various memories
to cope with different applications
Let’s take an example
The cellphones we use
or high power consuming, high-performance servers
It’s actually a relative thing
We know the power demand is very large
then in memory applications
we might need to develop higher speed memories
But it may consume more power
to meet the demand of existing servers now
we still need high speed memory like that
But with some common wearable devices
they might need very low power consumption
and the operating speed doesn’t have to be so fast
there’s no need for high speed demand
So the design of memory
has to be optimized as
a low power consuming one
but more reliable
without needing to recharge frequently
This is our demand
So to cope with different needs
memories will have different specializations
Thanks for your elaboration
With AI and consumer electronics market growing vigorously
Whether it’s the semiconductor market of
logic chips or memory
competition will only become more intense
Whoever holds the new design
will gain an early advantage
and dominate the entire market
In this competition
there’s another realm that can’t be ignored
besides chip architecture tech
That’s the equipment for manufacturing chips
For example
when China is unable to obtain
ASML’s EUV machine
it‘ll impact the development of the whole country’s semiconductor industry
What is EUV used for?
What are the key factors in the semiconductor manufacturing process
we have to pay attention to?
The answers to these questions
shall be uncovered in our next episode
See you next time